Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for
computer architecture for everybody. In this
walkthrough, we are going to do some more
work with our CDC 6504 emulator. We're
going
to build
our first loop. So, let me go ahead and load
that loop up and then turn on the
assembler
so
we can see it. Oh, not that one. We're not
going to change it. That would
be where we
would change
it. , let's view the assembly. We just want
to be able to look at it when we're near it.
Okay.
, and so this is not going to use any
memory. So I can just leave
the view
assembly
over here. Actually can bring it all the way
over here because we're not going
to get
into
the second second half of the instruction
memory because we're done here. So let's get
a review of
what we're going to do. So this is a Python
for the X register in range five because
this is going to go this is going to be a
loop that goes 0 1 2 3 4 and then when it
hits five
it's going to jump out. It's not going to
execute the body of the loop for the value
five. As soon
as it hits five, as soon as it's equal to
five, we're going to jump out of the loop.
So the first
thing to note is this syntax of a label.
labels are not actually in the machine
language. They're
making it so that we don't have to put
numbers in this jump instruction or the
branch if
equal instruction. So, we can basically say,
"Hey, assembler, you're pretty good at
keeping track of
stuff." This loop is going to turn into an
address and we're going to jump to an
address, which is a
number, or we're going to jump to an offset.
And please calculate the offset. do all that
calculation for me so I don't have to put
numbers in here. So these aren't really
instructions,
they're pseudo instructions much the data
pseudo instruction. So let's take a look at
how these things end up in the machine
language. So let's take a look at the jump
to loop. That
jump to loop is the jump back up to the top.
And so we're sitting here at location
0x06
and
that's a jump instruction. And the the loop
is the address which is what the
program
counter is
going to get set to and that's going to set
the program counter to one which
means it's
going to
jump to instruction one and that is the
compare instruction. So the calculation of
this number
one is done by the assembler as it looks at
this loop symbol and it re keeps track of
it. Right?
So it took two to two passes. You can
calculate it backwards jumps but forward
jumps are a little bit
harder. Now the BEQ is even a little bit
trickier. Okay? Because of course the BEQ
checks the Z flag.
If the two last comparison was equal then
the result of that subtraction would be
zero. And so
and so we're going to be EEQ. So here's the
BEQ at at PC location 0x03. And
then we take
a look
at the immediate. So this immediate you
would it's going to jump to location
8 which
is the
end of the program which is a break
instruction but you look at this offset and
that's a three
011 is a three and so what this is is this
is a relative offset again computed by the
assembler on
our behalf. Now, it turns out that this
three is going to be added to the current
program counter,
but it's not added to four. It's actually
added to five. And that's because the
program counter
retrieved the BEQ instruction. Then it
retrieved the immediate instruction. And as
a side effect,
it incremented the PC. And so the PC once
this BEQ is executing is five. So 5 + 3 is
8. And you listen as you read it. It'll
it'll have computed the 5 + 3.
it'll know
that this
is five and it'll add three to it and it'll
know eight. And so when we're narrating this
execution,
you'll hear it talking about branching to
eight when 8 is not really sitting here in
the base 2. Okay. So let's go ahead and do
some steps. I'll take it slow at the
beginning
and then we'll speed it up. PC0 clear X
register. So we cleared the X register but
again it already
was zero because the program was just
starting but the PCs moved up to one. The
zero is set
because we cleared the X register. We
touched the X register. We did a
calculation
which
means we set it to zero. Okay. And that sets
the Z flag. The next instruction is going to
be compare to five. PC0x01. Compare X
register with immediate 0x0. Okay.
Now the
interesting
thing is that is not Z because it's not
equal. It does a subtraction. So it takes 0
minus five,
but it didn't store the result of that. It
just set the flags. And so that compare
instruction
doesn't change registers. It just changes
flags. So now we're at the point where Z is
not set and
N is set. And so the fix we're going to do
is we're going to run this BEQ instruction.
That means if the Z is set, we're going to
jump to end. And end is three characters,
three bytes beyond location five. But in
this first time, we're not going to jump
because the
Z flag is not set. So let's do a step.
You'll see it's going to just jump over it
to location 5 PC3
address. So you'll notice it calculated the
5 + 3 equals 8. But because the Z flag is
not set,
it just went to PC5 and didn't touch the PC.
So you can always think of a
branch or a jump as a setting of the PC
value. But in this case,
it computed a relative offset of the current
PC, which was five plus three.
And that
would have
been where we jumped. So the next thing
we're going to do after we didn't
jump is
we're going
to increment X PC increment X register. So
now X is one. It's not negative and it's not
zero.
And the next thing we're going to do is
we're going to jump back up to location
one.
So this
is an absolute jump to location one. Whereas
the branch EQ was a positive offset jump.
PC06 jump to address one. So we're back at
one. You see the PC is one. And
now the next
thing
we're doing is going to do the comparison.
PC01. Compare X register with immediate
0x05. Now one is
less than five. So we get the N flag. So
we're not going to file this branch. PC0x03
branch if equal
address 0x08 didn't branch. Now we're going
to increment PC05 increment X register.
And
now we're
going to do an absolute jump a goto. PC0x06
jump to address one. So you let's
let's go
ahead
and just run it for a while. We'll wait.
Maybe I'll try to stop it when X is three
and then
see what's going on. So let's just run it.
PC0x01. Compare X register with immediate
0x05. PC0X03
branch if equal address 0x08 PC 0x05.
Increment X register PC 0x06. Jump to
address one. PC0X01.
Compare X register with immediate 0x05. PC
0x03 branch if equal address 0x08 PC 0x05
increment X
register PC 0x06 jump to address one P Okay,
so now we are jumped to address one. I I
caught it
halfway through it. Okay, I did the compare
and it fell through still because it's not
equal. The
next time we're coming up, X is going to be
five. So, I'm going to start stepping at
this point. ,
, we're going to I think this is, , oh, no,
it's we I stopped it before the beq. Okay.
So,
so it's still negative because we checked to
see if four and if if four was less than
five and it
is. So that the the the n is still. So,
we're going to branch x03 branch equal
address 0x08.
Do one more. This is going to be the
increment. PC0x05 increment
X register. Now
we're going to do
an absolute jump back up to the top of the
loop. PC06 jump to address one. Okay, here
we are. So
look, X is now five. This is a top tested
loop. The next thing we're going
to do is
we're going
to compare it and watch the little Z flag.
Happy little Z flag turn on. One step.
PC0x01 compare X
register with immediate 0x05. There we go.
So the Z register is now set and the BEQ is
going to read
the Z the Z flag actually not register. I
think as one bit registers. Okay. And so the
BEQ is
going to jump and remember it's going to
take this three 1 and add it to five and
jump to eight. So
let's party. PC0x03 branch if equal address
0x08 and now we're at X08 and then we're
going to do PC
X08 break no printed output. So there's no
printed output because we didn't store
anything. We didn't
store anything in the memory. We are just
showing you how loops work. Okay. So I hope
this has been
helpful in a simple loop. In a bit we're
going to do both. So, this is both
a loop
and an
if test. And then we're going to do a couple
more that get a little bit more complicated.